<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the state of the case between the ever-honourable Parliament and the officers of the Army, that fell out on the eleventh and twelfth of October, 1659. Published to prevent mistakes, by a lover of his countrey and freedom E.D.</title>
            <author>Chillenden, Edmund, fl. 1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3879A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1000_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866866</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866866</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119154</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79513)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119154)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E1000[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the state of the case between the ever-honourable Parliament and the officers of the Army, that fell out on the eleventh and twelfth of October, 1659. Published to prevent mistakes, by a lover of his countrey and freedom E.D.</title>
                  <author>Chillenden, Edmund, fl. 1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.C.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>E.D. = Edmund Chillenden.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct. 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119154:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION OF THE STATE of the CASE Between the ever Honourable PARLIAMENT AND THE OFFICERS OF THE ARMY, That fell out on the eleventh and twelfth of <hi>October,</hi> 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed to prevent mistakes,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Lover of his Countrey and Freedom E. <hi>D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> J. C. 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119154:2"/>
            <head>A TRUE RELATION OF The State of the Caſe BETWEEN Parliament and ſome Aſpiring Officers of the ARMY.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THere is no Nation under Heaven, I conceive, hath met with more turnings and ſhakings, and hath had ſorer and deeper deſigns againſt it then this Common-wealth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And truly all things duly conſidered, there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of people under the whole Heaven, that have been ſo great enemies to its peace, and ſettlement, as ſome Officers of the Army, witneſs <hi>the interruption of this Parliament the</hi> 20th <hi>April</hi> 1653. then routing the little Juncto Parliament (ſo named) made and ſet up by themſelves, and then ſetting up <hi>Oliver that Uſurper</hi> to be Protector, then proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Son <hi>Richard, diſſolving his Parliament</hi> plucking him down, then inviting this honourable <hi>Parliament</hi> to take on them that Truſt, that they ſtood cloathed with by the Peoples choice, and now only out of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition interrupt them again.</p>
            <p n="3">3. So that it is plain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they have not only been the great hinderers of the Peace and good ſettlement of the Common-wealth, <hi>but lust, ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Covetiouſneſs haveng poſſeſſed their hearts</hi>) are likely to prove <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119154:2"/>Vipors</hi> to this Common-wealth, even to eat out the very Bowels thereof, ſo that truly it is a ſign we are fallen into the laſt times ſpoken of by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4. <hi>and all thoſe thoſe things there ſpoken of, for ehe most part, theſe ambitions Officers of thr Army are guilty of,</hi> viz. <hi>Lovers of themſelves, covetous boasters-proud blaſphemers, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, unthankeful, unholy, Truce-breakers, falſe accuſars, traytors, high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, lovers of pleaſures more then lovers of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That they inordinately love themſelves, is clear to all the world, becauſe that in all theſe turnings, they have only made themſelves great, as to be named Lords Sir Reverence, and to ger great Eſtates, as in the Protectors time to have 1000 <hi>li.</hi> year a piece to be of his Councel to oppreſſe the Nation, and to defeat the inferiour Officers, Seamen and Souldiers of their pay, they being by them run in Arrear nigh a year, which they never by this Parliament were ſithence the War, but payed to a day, and now this <hi>Parliament,</hi> would have payed all their Arrears, and have ſetled conſtrut pay for them and the Navy, which may appear, <hi>by thier Votes of the</hi> 11. <hi>of Octob inant.</hi> 1659</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>They are lovers of themſelves,</hi> becauſe in all <hi>their Propoſals</hi> to this <hi>Parliament, viz:</hi> that from <hi>Darby,</hi> drawn up and ſigned by. <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Brigade,</hi> and their <hi>Reproſentation</hi> delivered to the <hi>Houſe the</hi> 5th <hi>instant,</hi> ſigned by 230 Officers, they do not propoſe one thing for the good of this Common-wealth, nor for the good of <hi>the honest people,</hi> or <hi>Good old cauſe;</hi> but wholly for themſelves, as that <hi>Fleetwood</hi> may be General, <hi>Lambert</hi> may be the next General Officer, that is, to be <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor General of the Army of England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland, Disborrow</hi> the next, to be <hi>Leiut. Gen. of the horſe,</hi> and <hi>General Monk</hi> to be <hi>Major Gen. of the Foot,</hi> to have their Arrears, conſtant pay, and power without the <hi>Parliament,</hi> to turn out, and put in to die Army, and do not they love themſelves very well? but the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> the <hi>good people,</hi> and this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> but a little.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly, <hi>They are Covetous boasters,</hi> for what a ſtir and ado do they keep in trumpeting their own honour, and the great valour they ſhewed, and jeopardy they were in at <hi>VVinnington</hi> Bridge, by Sir <hi>George Booths</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and this they do twice in their laſt Repreſentation of <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. when alaſsit is well known there was not ſo great ſervice or vallour ſhewed or done in that buſineſes, as hath been done by many <hi>a ſingle Troop</hi> of this <hi>Army,</hi> and what is all this cry for? Is it not that they may be made great, and have large pay, to tho oppreſſion and ruinc of the good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and herein they are covetous Boaſters-</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119154:3"/>
            <p n="4">4ly, <hi>They are proud Blaſphemers,</hi> becauſe they commit <hi>Treaſon, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Rapine, rnd ſpoyl on the people of this Common-wealthy,</hi> and they ſay, <hi>God teacheth, directeth and commands them to do it;</hi> They breake <hi>Covenants, Promiſes, Faith Protestations, Engagements, Declarations, Sollemn Appeals to God, with hands lifted up to Heaven,</hi> in the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn way that could be, <hi>Repent of aebellion and Treaſon,</hi> and the next day <hi>repent, they did repent,</hi> and <hi>commit greater Treaſons and Rebellions,</hi> and yet ſay <hi>God is amongst them,</hi> and uſe <hi>Gods Name and his Ordinances</hi> to colour all their <hi>villainous wickedneſſes,</hi> this is <hi>proud blaſphemy;</hi> yea ſuch as never was in the world, worſe than <hi>Rabſhakahs, Eſay</hi> 37. For theſe have not only diſpiſed God, but made him to colour all their evils, by the which they have made not only this Common-wealth, the Good old Cauſe, the <hi>Churches of Christ,</hi> and all <hi>Profeſſion of Rdligion rediculous contemptible, a ſcorn &amp; hiſſing to all the world, and God his name and them that dwell in the Heaven is reproached &amp; blaſphemed by their wicked vile deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>They are diſobedient,</hi> becauſe look in all their Declarations, there Engage-ments, Propoſals, and Repreſentations of the Officers of the Army to this Parliament, eſpecially their Declaration to invite the Members to return to their Truſt, of <hi>April</hi> 6, 1659. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>That the <hi>Long Parliament</hi> conſiſting of the Members, which continued their ſitting until the 20th. of <hi>April</hi> 1653. were eminent aſſertors of that Cauſe (the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi>) and had a ſpecial preſence of God with them, and were ſignally bleſſed in that work; And there fore we do hereby moſt earneſtly deſire the Parliament conſiſting of thoſe Members who continued to ſit ſince the year 1648. until the 20th of <hi>April,</hi> 1653. to return to the exerciſe and diſcharge of their Truſt, and we ſhall be ready in our places to yield them as becometh us, our utmoſt aſſiſtance to ſit in ſafety for the improving the preſent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for ſetling and ſecuring the peace and freedom of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in a Letter of <hi>May</hi> the 18. from General <hi>Monk,</hi> and the Officers in <hi>Scotland,</hi> pag. 5. <hi>You may reſt aſſured with greatest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that we ſhall appear in your DEFENCE and VINDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION of your AUTHORITY, against the Oppreſſion of all ARBITRARY Powers whatſoever.</hi> And in their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of <hi>October</hi> 5, 1659. <hi>pag.</hi> 2. they ſay; <q>That neither we nor our faithful brethren of the Northern Bridgade who ſigned the ſaid Petition and Propoſals did deſigne and intend the inturruption of the Parliament, the prejudice of the peace of this Commonwealth, or any
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119154:3"/>other by and ſiniſter reſpect, not becoming the Truſt repoſed in us. And in <hi>pag.</hi> 9. Wherefore through the help of our God we ſhall be found (notwithſtanding all indeavou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to the contrary) faithfull to you and this Commonwealth;</q> And ſo in many other Papers from <hi>Ire and</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> where they do ſay as much as can be ſaid by any men; Nay many of them to make their wickedneſs the greater, <hi>when they took their Commiſſions,</hi> not being required, did voluntarily <hi rend="margQuotes">proniſe in the Parliament to ſerve the Parliament with all faithfulneſs &amp; ſubmiſſion as to the Supream Authority of this Commonwealth:</hi> And in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Lambert;</hi> for when he came for his <hi>Commiſſion, the Parliament</hi> were about two hours debating whether he ſhould have Commiſſion under them or no; but being called in to receive his Commiſſion, when he had it, <hi>did deſire leave of the Parliament to ſpeak a few words,</hi> which he was permitted to do. <hi rend="margQuotes">And there and then did he promiſe the PARLIAMENT he would ſerve them with all faithfulneſs and obedience; and when he could ſerve them no longer, he would give up his Commiſſion to them, and lye down at the feet of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or words to this effect.</hi> And ſo did Colonel <hi>Rich</hi> almoſt <hi>in totidem vibis.</hi> And <hi>Fleetwood</hi> did promiſe the Parliament the? 12th. of <hi>October</hi> 1659. (on the parting the Act for vacating his Commiſſion as Lieutenant General of the Army, and putting it under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Seamen) that he would <hi>faithfully acquieſs,</hi> and further to ſhew their diſobedience &amp; jugling, that when they had one <hi>October</hi> 13, 1659. beſieged all the Parliament-men in their Lodgings in <hi>White Hall,</hi> and ſtopt all the paſſages that none could go to <hi>Westminster,</hi> and had vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently turned back the Speaker. The Council of State made an Order for all the Forces to withdraw and march to their Quarters, as well thoſe for the Parliament as thoſe that were againſt them; thoſe for the Parliament in obedience to the Order marched away, and ſo did moſt of the other, but <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Sidenham</hi> contrary to their truſt, and like Traytors in diſobedience to the Councils Order, cauſed two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Foot to take poſſeſſion of the Parliament-Houſe took away by violence the Keyes from Mr. <hi>Hully,</hi> and have by that means kept the Parliament by violence ever ſince from doing their duties. Who ever can truſt ſo <hi>vile,</hi> and <hi>faithleſs, falſe-hetrted, deſſembling, hypocritical a people.</hi> I can liken this people to none for the heighth of deſimulation, <hi rend="margQuotes">but to <hi>Henry</hi> 4th of <hi>France,</hi> about the miſcaror of the poor <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> there ſee that Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>They are, I mean the ambitions Officers of the Army, unholy</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119154:4"/>becauſe they ſin and commit Rapin, Treaſon, and Rebellion, and then diſſemble repentance, and commit it again, as at <hi>VVindſor</hi> in 1648, at <hi>James</hi> 1652, at <hi>VVallingford-houſe</hi> in 1659. and many other places at ſeveral other times, but now the light of their diſſembling, jugling, hypocritical wickedneſs they ſhew in the ſight of the Sun. <hi rend="margQuotes">For Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday the 11 of <hi>Gctober</hi> 1659. in the Chappel at <hi>VVhite-hall,</hi> Packer, and Spencer and divers others repented of their repentance,</hi> and like the <hi>Dog</hi> 
               <hi rend="margQuotes">ſwallow up again their own Vomit, that in them the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb ſpoken of by the Apoſtles is verified, 2 <hi>Petér</hi> 2.22.</hi> Mr. <hi>Packer</hi> remember what you ſaid in <hi>Richards</hi> Parliament, we ſay remember how you confeſſed your ſins, in having a hand in breaking up Parliamentss, and bringing that ruine that is none on this Land, <hi>and promiſed before God, Angels, and Men,</hi> never to have a hand in it any more; <hi>Oh falſe man!</hi> How do'ſt thou dare to look God in the face? We wonder thou canſt lye on thy Pillow and ſleep, for fear the judgement of God ſhould overtake thee; be ſure it will, if thou doeſt not now in good earneſt repent of all thy horrible hypocriſies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thou valiant</hi> Copta Spencer, that never fought but with a good Dinner, and at that ſport thou art an <hi rend="margQuotes">excellent good Trencher Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and as ſtout as any man alive, and art none of the leſſer Lyers,</hi> and deſſembler amongſt the <hi>Holy Ones,</hi> for thou canſt write Letters from thy Quarters <hi>August</hi> 2 1659. to Mr. <hi>Kiffen,</hi> that all thoſe poor people might be deluded, to pray for valiant <hi>Copta Spencer</hi> that he may do that he never did in his life, <hi>fight beat his Enemies,</hi> for now ſaith <hi>Spencer</hi> he and we are ſurrounded, and to morrow we are to be ingaged this was ſo <hi>notoriouſly,</hi> as could be told by man, for there was no envy viſible by above 60 miles therefore its believed thou meants <hi>poor Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> that they ſhould pray thou mighteſt have a good ſtomack to thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, <hi>for Hunger is all the Enemits thou dareſt to encounter with;</hi> tuſh theſe ate but ſmall things to their <hi>Solemn Meetings,</hi> and confeſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and his People <hi rend="margQuotes">of their wandering and going in divers wayes from righteous and equal paths, going in the dark and ſtumbling;</hi> and then bleſs God that there eyes are open, and now they ſee the truth, and there is great joy, and anon this light is become their darkneſs, and their former dark paths (they all having gotten <hi>Catts</hi> eyes) they are now the true light ways, and now they are as joccond as may be they are now in the ready road of deſtruction, but I pray you <hi>brave aſpiring Officers</hi> let us ask this one queſtion of you (though ſome ſay ſome of you are Atheiſts) Did you beleeve there was a God when you made your promiſes, when you profeſſed your faiths; when you ingaged, I, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119154:4"/>that in outward ſhew to a God, wee ſay; if then you did believe there was a God, you beleeve there is no God now, or you ſin and commit horrible wickedneſs againſt God, and the light of your own hearts and Conſciences, and are we are afraid incorruptable, <hi rend="margQuotes">that his vengeance may overtake you to the utmoſt, for you are contrary to all men and pleaſe not God, but every day are filling up your ſins to that end, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.15, 16.</hi> Therefore conſider betimes before it be too late, and repent and do your firſt works, for do you think the Nation will ever truſt you that have thus faſly <hi rend="margQuotes">betrayed their Lives, Liberties and Eſtates, to your own luſt?</hi> No, no, never think it, for God will make your very Regiments rebel againſt you, and that is not to be feared but in few Moneths will come to paſs and you ſhall not withſtand it.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <hi>They are, I mean the Officers of the Army, falſe aceu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> for they ſay and lay to the Parliaments charge theſe ſeveral falſe particulars.</p>
            <p>That they were and did carry on a <hi>Presbyterian Deſigne,</hi> and would have ſetled the <hi>Presbyterian Government,</hi> this is falſe and envy it ſelf cannot prove it in the leaſt; and if 40 or 50 Members may be beleived, they ſay and do averre, there was not one man that ever did move fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence their laſt Sitting, any ſuch matter or any thing tending to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They ſay the <hi>Parliament would have made a Law to have perſecuted the godly people of this Nation for Conſcience ſake in matter of Religion,</hi> that is, <hi>the hook,</hi> that the Officers of the Army have baited, by which they have chached the Churches of the Congregational way to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of their wickedneſs in interrupting this Parliament, but they are but meerly abuſed as the people of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were by <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.11. <hi>Being in the ſimplicity of their hearts, for they know not the thinge.</hi> For it is falſe as ever any thing was; as may be ſeen by the <hi>vote of the Committee,</hi> that is and hath been Printed into News Books, and I am aſſured they would have ſetled Liberty of Conſcience ſo clear, as no man ſhould ever have had any more fear of perſecution from the Magiſtrate. <hi>No it ſhould not have been in the power of future Parliam. to have medled with it, it ſhould have been a ctanding Fundamental,</hi> as the <hi>Vote</hi> it ſelf will evidence, <hi>viz. at the Committees for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſitting in the Speakers Chrmber,</hi> October 8, 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the Supream delegated power is not intruſted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the profeſſion of any perſon or perſons, who profeſs Faith in God the Father, and in Jeſus Chriſt God manifeſt in the fleſh, and in God the Holy Spirit, God bleſſed for evermore, and do acknowledge the holy Scriptures of the Old and new Teſtament, to be the revealed or witten
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119154:5"/>word or will of God, but ought to give due encouragement, and equall Protection to them in the profeſſion of their Faith, and exerciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whilſt they abuſe not this Liberty, to the Civil injury of others, or diſturbance of others in their way of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>This is clear and full, I wonder what we would have deſired more, but put the caſe that it had been true, as it is falſe, muſt we for fear of <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for Religion rebell and commit Treaſon?</hi> Surely, the <hi>Goſpel of Christ teacheth no ſuch thing,</hi> but patiently to ſuffer and not to reſiſt &amp; riſe up againſt the <hi>Supream Authority,</hi> and throw that down to ſet up Liberty of Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly, <hi>Theſe Officers ſay they ſat</hi> 6 <hi>Moneths and did nothing,</hi> This is ſo great a ſlander, as I wonder with what impudence they can affirm ſuch a thing, as all that have but read the Diurnals, may ſee, the baſeneſs of this ſlander. Firſt they ſpent one month nigh hand, to put and ſettle things in away ſo as they might run with ſome eaſe and that they might keep the head above water, from ſinking in that <hi>diſorder and confuſion as Oliver the late Uſurper,</hi> and his Son <hi>Richard</hi> by the means of theſe Officers of <hi>Army,</hi> had brought this <hi>Nation and Common-wealth into.</hi> 2ly, Then the Armies Act of Indempnity and free pardon. 3ly, The Acts for the ſeveral Militias of the Counties, and Cities of this Nation, which took up much time. 4ly, the paſſing of all the Commiſſions for the Officers of the Armies of <hi>England Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> which could not quickly be diſpatched. 5ly, Then Sir <hi>George Booths rebellion,</hi> which did hinder them nigh 2 months. 6ly, <hi>The Acts for the union of Scotland and ſettlement of Ireland,</hi> which were very long Acts, and of great weight and concernment, and were not to be ſlightly paſſed, they took up a very great deal of time in a Grand Committee. 7ly, The Act for Sequſtrations. 8ly. The Act for the Keepers of the Great Scal. 9. The ſending the Plenepotentiaries to the <hi>Sound,</hi> and many other matters which we cannot remember, that we can teſtefie they laboured like hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes night and day: therefore here they ly and ſlander the Parliament, for they are free from this their abuſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>They ſay they would not have proſecuted against Sir George Booth, and his party,</hi> Oh envy it it ſelf! who can with any face of honeſty faſten this on the Parliament? Can things be done in a day? was all Examinations taken and ready; was the depth of the plot found out? All know it was univerſally laid, over all Nation, and therefore the more need of time, to take all Examinations, for the more clear and full diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of and proof of all, that there might be the moree Juſtice done, as ſo great &amp; horrible a Plot did deſerve.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119154:5"/>
            <p>But if there were any delay, it was in in <hi>Sr. Henry Vain,</hi> who had the whole to report, and delayed it, till he was called upon again and again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And then,</hi> did not theſe ſlanderers the Officers of the Army, <hi>hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Parliament</hi> at leaſt three weeks by their <hi>fooliſh papers,</hi> it is more then probable that theſe Officers would not have Sr. <hi>George and his party proſecuted,</hi> becauſe they have obſtructed and interrupted the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the way and means to it; and indeed it is ſtrange, that the <hi>Army ſhould deſire their proſecution,</hi> when they have done ten times worſe, for Sr. <hi>George and his party</hi> never did ingage to be true and faithful to this Parliament, the Officers of the Army did ingage, and they were for a free <hi>Parliament,</hi> and the Officers of the Army are for no <hi>Parliaments nor Laws,</hi> but what muſt come under the <hi>teſt of their ſwords,</hi> and in all theſe things they ſpeak falſly to deceive, and in them as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eze.</hi> 22.9. <hi>Are men that carry tales to ſhed blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what is the State of this great caſe, that the Nation muſt be ruined, and all Authority kicked at, and pluckt up by the roots,</hi> the <hi>caſe</hi> is the ſame it was at the firſt with the <hi>King and Parliament,</hi> whether the <hi>King</hi> ſhould have the command of the <hi>Militia,</hi> or the <hi>Parliament;</hi> and ſo it is now, <hi>whether the Parliament ſhould have the command of the Army, or Luit. Gen. Fleetwood, I had almoſt ſaid Lambert,</hi> for ſo it is and will be, how cunningly ſoever it is carried.</p>
            <p>And it aroſe thus, aſſoon as indeed <hi>God had beaten down Sr. George Booths Army,</hi> by taking away their hearts, <hi>Cheſter quited</hi> and <hi>Cherck Caſtle delivered, Major Creed</hi> is ſent up with a Letter giving a full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all, and for that he and Lieut. Col. <hi>Dukenfield,</hi> had given them each 250 l. and that day L. Gen. <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> moved the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that <hi>Lambert</hi> might be made <hi>Major General</hi> of the <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> as formerly, to this the <hi>Houſe</hi> giveth their <hi>Negative,</hi> as by experience we find they had good cauſe ſo to do, but yet they gave <hi>Lambert</hi> a 1000 l.<hi>to buy him a Jewel,</hi> as an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment from the <hi>Parliament</hi> for his good ſervice, and we think every man will Judge, it a good reward, but this did not pleaſe <hi>his Majeſty,</hi> for ſo he muſt be called ſhortly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then Major Creed</hi> returning and <hi>Capt. Brown,</hi> to the <hi>Northern Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade,</hi> where meeting with <hi>Col. Zanchy and Col. Axtel</hi> and others, as they were returning to <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>Cheſter,</hi> they did conſider in their hearts, what they ſhould do by way of returning thanks to God <hi>(and as Major Creed declared to the Council of Officers of the Army at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119154:6"/>Wallingford-houſe)</hi> they went to <hi>prayer,</hi> and <hi>God ſet this upon their hearts, that is, that paper that was ſigned by the Northern Brigade, and ſent up to London by Capt. Brown, to the Claſſis;</hi> this is <hi>horrible deluſions,</hi> and no leſs then <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt the great <hi>God of Heaven,</hi> to father ſuch things of him; will any think <hi>God told Creed</hi> and the other Officers, that they ſhould appoint the <hi>Parliament</hi> to make <hi>Fleetwood General,</hi> and <hi>Lambert Major General of the Army of England and Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Disborrow to be Lieut. Gen. of the Horſe,</hi> and <hi>Monk to be Major General of the Foot,</hi> or elſe the <hi>Parliament ſhall be interrupted;</hi> ſurely, they mean the <hi>god of this world, that ruleth in the hearts of the children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, as they are;</hi> they indeed ſay they went to prayers, juſt <hi>like the Conjurors,</hi> begin all things in <hi>Gods Name,</hi> how wicked ſoever it is, according to the old Proverb, <hi>In Nomine Domini incipit omne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> O good Lord what a ſad condition is this Common-wealth in, that have ſuch <hi>Commanders</hi> over their <hi>Armies,</hi> that are guided by <hi>Enthuſiaſms,</hi> ſo that now if their <hi>hearts</hi> be prompt by <hi>luſt and covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> to take away all <hi>Law, Property</hi> and <hi>Rigth,</hi> from every man, that he by <hi>Law</hi> hath, to that which is known, they muſt do it, for God ſet it on their hearts, he told them ſo; this they ſay, and is very likely it will come to ſuch a matter, for the <hi>worſhipful Doctor Worſely,</hi> did preach ſuch a doctrine at <hi>Wallingford-houſe,</hi> before the <hi>Venerable Aſſembly of Officers, that all our Lawes, Lives, Liberties, Eſtates, were in the diſpoſe of the Army,</hi> and this paſſed without the leaſt <hi>controul,</hi> and indeed, they muſt ſo practiſe, or elſe they cannot raiſe any money, as you will ſee hereafter; well this paper is ſent from <hi>Darby to London by Capt. Brown</hi> (and not onely thither, but to <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that before it was known here to <hi>Lieutenant General,</hi> or any of the Officers, a moſt preſumptious thing if it were true, which we cannot believe, that any particular Officers did dare to ſend a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to ingage the <hi>Armies of three Nations,</hi> without making it known to the <hi>Chief Officers,</hi> as cloſe as it is carried, and it is very probable, that the Officers were the Plotters of it, becauſe when they did know it, they were ſo far from diſcountenance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and puniſhing the Authors, as they fall in with them, and juſtifie them, as may be <hi>ſeen</hi> in their <hi>Repreſentation of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter the</hi> 5th. 1659. When this paper <hi>arrives at London,</hi> it taketh <hi>Lodging</hi> at <hi>White-Hall</hi> in <hi>Lamberts Quarters,</hi> and on Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day was there read, before twenty Officers; now <hi>Lambert</hi> did not know of it, till now, and when he and <hi>L. G. Fleetwood</hi> knew of it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119154:6"/>they did not <hi>approve of it</hi> (no, no more then a man that is very hungry approveth of good victuals ſuch as he liketh with all his heart) if they did not, why did not they ſtifle it in the birth and ſuppreſſe it, which they might have done if they had pleaſed; but they were ſo far from it, as they do give it countenance and all the furtherance they can, elſe why did not L. G. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> according to the commands of <hi>Parliament</hi> cauſe the Army to deſiſt; but that is ſo far from him as they juſtifie it, (as aforeſaid) by their Repreſentations of <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. 1659.</p>
            <p>And now their <hi>Repreſentation</hi> being come to the <hi>Houſe,</hi> they had <hi>thanks for their good expreſſions of their good affections to the Parliament,</hi> and that the <hi>Parliament</hi> would proceed to give them all <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> that may be, and on Saturday the 8. of <hi>Octob.</hi> they would go on their paper, and ſo did, and Monday and Tueſday following, as may be ſeen by <hi>the Votes that paſsed the Houſe</hi> (that have been printed in the News Books) how the <hi>Parliament</hi> did make all the ſpeed poſſible to have given them full <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to all their <hi>demands</hi> as it might ſtand with the <hi>honour of Parliament and the Freedom of Engliſhmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But behold <hi>while the Parliament is</hi> haſting to give them all juſt ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to their deſire, the <hi>Councel of Officers of the Army,</hi> order <hi>the Coppies</hi> of the <hi>repreſentations</hi> to the ſent to all the <hi>Regiments of horſe and foot, and to all gariſons in the</hi> 3. <hi>Nations</hi> to be by them ſigned and ſpeedily to be ſent to Mr. <hi>Samford,</hi> L. G. <hi>Fleetwoods Secretary,</hi> and ordered that thoſe nine Officers (that were by the <hi>Parliament</hi> uncommiſſionated) ſhould write a Letter under their hands and incloſe thoſe coppies, the which they did.</p>
            <p>Now this coming to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and they having <hi>proof of it,</hi> that they were a labouring as one man to <hi>combine against the Parliament,</hi> and to force them; they clearly did foreſee they could not ſit to make a perpetual Coordinate Senate, of which they expected to be there freely without being impoſed on, and rather then to do it they would die, therefore they were reſolved to try the <hi>obedience</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> whether they would <hi>acquieſce</hi> in ſuch <hi>reſolves as they ſhall make or no,</hi> that they might have good ground to know they ſat freely, and were by them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>the Supream Authority</hi> and the <hi>Army their ſervants,</hi> from whom they took all their <hi>commiſſions,</hi> which <hi>very act</hi> if there were no more ſhould have taught them <hi>ſubjection,</hi> therefore now it came to this iſſue, whether the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall <hi>come to the Army,</hi> and diſpoſe of them, or <hi>Lieutenant General Fleetwood, or Lambert,</hi> and whether the <hi>Parliameni</hi> ſhall be <hi>Master,</hi> and the Army be the <hi>Servant,</hi> or the <hi>Parliament be the ſlave,</hi> to ſit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119154:7"/>there, and by their <hi>authority make ſuch Lawes,</hi> and raiſe ſuch monies, on the people, as they the <hi>Officers of the Army</hi> would force, and compell them to, and thereby oppreſſe, and even totally give away all our <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> at one blow, and make us ſlaves for ever, which they were not at all in the leaſt willing to do; and upon this ground the Parliament did proceed againſt thoſe nine Officers, and to the Alteration of the Conduct of the Army, as you may ſee by the Act of Parliament, and Votes of the 12. of <hi>October,</hi> 1659.</p>
            <p>And we would fain know, what the Parliament could do leſſe then they did, having ſo clear profit, under their own hands, and divers other <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> be ſides, is it any new thing the Parliament hath done, have they not former <hi>Preſidents many,</hi> look but back to about <hi>Feb.</hi> 1645. and you will find, they took away the Commiſſions of the <hi>Earls of</hi> Eſſex, Warwick, Mancheſters, <hi>Earls of</hi> Stamfords, &amp; Darbith, <hi>Sir</hi> William Wallers, Maſſeyes, Gells, Lawhorns, <hi>and divers others;</hi> did theſe, <hi>jeopard</hi> their <hi>lives</hi> in the <hi>high places</hi> of the <hi>Field,</hi> as well as theſe <hi>Officers?</hi> Yes that they did, but then the doctrine of Rebellion was <hi>not</hi> learned by them.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>here is the plain caſe,</hi> and the <hi>miſerable condition,</hi> we are <hi>brought to,</hi> whether we ſhall ſuffer, all <hi>Authority</hi> in our old and ancient, <hi>Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors the Parliament,</hi> the great <hi>boundary</hi> of all our <hi>Liberties,</hi> againſt Tyranny and Slavery, to be thus trodden under foot, and be ſubject to ſome three or four mens wills, and Luſt; <hi>viz. Fleetwood, Lambert, Desborow, and Berry;</hi> for ſo it is, but we hope all true <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> will <hi>abominate it;</hi> for let them ſay what they will, and pretend never ſo much, <hi>Tyrants, yea, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Tyrants they muſt be;</hi> for Lawes, for what they do, they have none, and make Lawes, they we are ſure cannot; and <hi>King James</hi> ſaith, he is <hi>A Tyrant</hi> that ruleth without Law, and this is true in theſe men.</p>
            <p>We would very fain know how they can <hi>raiſe any money,</hi> on the people, but by <hi>Tyranny,</hi> it being againſt the <hi>Fundamental Lawes of England,</hi> as <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and it <hi>it is declared by this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be High Treaſon,</hi> for any <hi>mony to be raiſed,</hi> without our own <hi>conſent in Parliament,</hi> ſee the words of the Act it ſelf. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And be it further enacted, that no perſon</hi> or perſons ſhall after the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>October,</hi> 1659. <hi>Aſseſs, Levy, Collect together, or receive any Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, Impost, Exciſe, Aſseſſement, Contribution, Tax, Tallage, or any ſumme, or ſummes of mony, or other Impoſitions whatſoever, upon the people of this Common-wealth, without their conſent in Parliament; or as by Law might
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119154:7"/>have been done before the third of</hi> November, 1640. <hi>And be it further enacted and declared, that every perſon offending, contrary to this Act, ſhall be, and is hereby judged to be guilty of High Treaſon, and ſhall for it ſuffer as in caſe of High Treaſon;</hi> How can they now raiſe money to have it, to pay the poor ſouldiers and Sea-men, no wayes but by <hi>rapine, Robbery, and Plunder,</hi> and what that will come to, no man knoweth.</p>
            <p>But if this <hi>Parliament</hi> had <hi>been let alone, they would have made this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion happy;</hi> and a flouriſhing Nation, in Trade: for by the firſt of <hi>Jan.</hi> next, they would have quite taken off from <hi>Trade,</hi> all <hi>Custome,</hi> and <hi>Exciſe;</hi> they had an Act of Parliament for that end, under conſideration; and have payed all the <hi>debts</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> yea the <hi>Publick Faith and all;</hi> and have <hi>ſetled</hi> us under <hi>a ſure</hi> and good government <hi>of Annuall and ſucceſſive Parliaments,</hi> that we ſhould not have feared every 6 months, to have bin a ruine to <hi>a new Government,</hi> which doth render us the moſt <hi>ridiculous people in the world,</hi> and indeed we have by the practiſes, and evill acting of the <hi>Officers of the Army, rendred Magistry, the most ridiculous, and contemptible things that can be,</hi> ſo that we are the <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>laughter</hi> of all Nations, that but hear of us.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>Brave Engliſh-men,</hi> ſtand for your <hi>Rights, Liberties, and Lawes,</hi> that you have <hi>bought</hi> with your <hi>money, purchaſed</hi> with your <hi>blood,</hi> and be not <hi>inſlaved</hi> by an <hi>Army,</hi> and to dye, rather then to pay one peny that is not levied by <hi>conſent in Parliament;</hi> keep your <hi>goods,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> your <hi>houſes</hi> againſt <hi>all</hi> that ſhall come either to <hi>quarter</hi> on you, or to <hi>levie, or gather mony</hi> of you, as you would againſt <hi>thieves, Rogues,</hi> &amp; <hi>Robbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> cry all, they are not for, but againſt <hi>A ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſon,</hi> we wonder men are ſo voyd of <hi>ſence;</hi> is not he that is <hi>Generall of an Army, a Prince?</hi> and who ever it is that doth meddle with the <hi>Civil affaires,</hi> not by <hi>authority</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> though it be (as the French-man ſaith) one twee three feier veeve <hi>Kings,</hi> or <hi>a Counſel,</hi> or <hi>Coordinate Senate for life,</hi> it is all, <hi>a ſingle perſon,</hi> and will devolve into it quickly; we hope all true <hi>Engliſh men</hi> wil never ſubject their necks to ſuch a yoak, to have men in higheſt authority for their lives, this will be worſe then then the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man yoak,</hi> and it will not laſt long, but muſt center in one, and then let the <hi>child</hi> be named; and if you pleaſe, let it <hi>be King,</hi> becauſe it is a ſhort word, and you ſee quickly learned.</p>
            <p>But let them do what they can, they will not, nor ſhall they long ſtand; God ſhall, and ſurely God will confound them, as he did the <hi>King,</hi> and that great <hi>Tyrant, Oliver,</hi> that great <hi>aſpiring trayterly Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> who by his cheats and hypocriſies, deep diſſimulations, pretending
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119154:8"/>religion, couzened and deceived all the poor <hi>honest Church-men,</hi> and ſo do and will theſe men, how fair ſoever they promiſe, they can do no good, that ſhall be laſting, becauſe it is built and layed on an unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous foundation, it is laid in <hi>Treaſon, Rebellion, Hypocriſie,</hi> lying, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, yea, in horrid <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> and yet theſe are the men that pretend to ſet up the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> among us; Surely when Chriſt cometh he will not need the luſt, Ambition, Covetouſneſſe, Hypocriſie, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, Lying, Rebelling Trayterouſneſſe of people, that are no more to be confided in, then the Devil that is their father, for his works they do, therefore they are his children and ſervants, for his ſervants they are whom they obey, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. <hi>John</hi> 8.45. How is it poſſible theſe men can think to proſper when they are guilty, and muſt be guilty of more horrid wickedneſſes, treaſons and rebellions; <hi>For had Zimri peace that ſlew his master?</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.31. And do theſe men think to have peace that have not onely ſlain <hi>one Maſter,</hi> but divers; <hi>This Parliament twice, April,</hi> 20. 1653, then the little <hi>Junto:</hi> then this laſt and greateſt, <hi>this Parliament, now this</hi> 10. <hi>of October,</hi> 1659. Surely <hi>if</hi> Cain <hi>ſhall be avenged ſeven fould, truly</hi> Lamech <hi>ſeventy and ſeven foold,</hi> Gen. 4.24. And bleſſe not your ſelves becauſe you have not yet been brought to judgement, <hi>therefore you do har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den your hearts according to</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11 <hi>for God will come and that ſuddenly,</hi> Jude 15. <hi>to execute judgement upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly</hi> (as you are) <hi>among them of all your ungodly deeds, which you have ungodlily committed, and of all the hard ſpeeches you have ſpoken of God and against him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well now I warrant you they promiſe very fair things, a very <hi>bleſſed</hi> and <hi>good Government;</hi> But how can this be when the foundation is nought? there is not any thing as to <hi>a Government,</hi> that can be ſetled without the <hi>peoples conſent in Parliament</hi> that will be in this <hi>Nation durable;</hi> have we not experience in the late <hi>great Tyrants dayes</hi> that nothing would down with this people, but what they ſet up by their <hi>Repreſentatives aſſembled in Parliament;</hi> for it is againſt the liberty and freedom of people, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Fundamental Laws of</hi> England, to have <hi>a Government</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> impoſed on them without and againſt their wills and conſent in <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but theſe men ſay they will ſettle the <hi>Righteous Laws of Christ,</hi> and ſo ſaid M. G. <hi>Hariſon,</hi> but it was not in his power; for when thoſe Laws and Chriſts government cometh to be ſetled, he will need none of your Commanders, eſpecially ſo baſe and wicked ones as theſe Officers are; for he will not ſettle it <hi>by might or power, but by his ſpirit,</hi> Zach, 4.6. <hi>he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119154:8"/>will make all hearts then willing to ſtoop to him in that day of his power,</hi> Pſal. 110.</p>
            <p>It is true, he was full of his impulſes of ſpirit and <hi>Enthuſiaſmes,</hi> and tell him of <hi>Magna Carta</hi> and <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> he would puffe at all theſe, and ſay we ſhall have Laws from Heaven, but he was forced to fly to <hi>Magna Carta</hi> in the <hi>Protectors time,</hi> and therefore till Chriſt come, let us have but our <hi>ancient and Fundamental Laws, and Liberties,</hi> we ſhall then do very well, and let us tell all theſe men where had we been in the late <hi>Tyrants time</hi> had it not been for our <hi>Laws;</hi> We remember a ſpeech of that <hi>Tyrants</hi> to Sergant <hi>Maynard</hi> and <hi>Twiſden</hi> when they came before him about Mr. <hi>Conyes caſe,</hi> ſaith he to them, <hi>You tell me it is againſt Magna Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, and Petition of Right; Magna Carta,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Magna Farta; Petition of Right, Petition of Shite: I have more ado to Conquer</hi> 2. <hi>or</hi> 3. <hi>muſty old Laws, then I have to Conquer</hi> 3. <hi>Nations.</hi> I and ſo not onely he, but all ſuch as he was ſhall find I hope the hardeſt task that ever they undertook.</p>
            <p>And this buſineſſe now is no other then <hi>Olivers was,</hi> it is but <hi>Hariſons ſpirit tranſmigrated</hi> into Sir <hi>Henry Vain, Salloway, Sidenham</hi> and others that <hi>Lambert</hi> doth now make uſe of, and it ſhall effect as little as he did at that time.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>moſt Noble Engliſhmen</hi> be not abuſed by their <hi>flatteries,</hi> nor drawn into <hi>ſnares</hi> to Petition them, and make addreſſes to them; they deſerve no addreſſe but a Halter and an Ax, and that muſt be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed by the hazzard of your lives and fortunes, and better dye, as Mr. <hi>Clement Cook</hi> ſaid in the Parl. 3 Carol. <hi>It is better to dye by the hand of a Forrain enemy then to be deſtroyed at home;</hi> and ſo we and our children had better dye with our ſwords in our hands in defence of our Laws and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, then to looſe all, and be enſlaved by an Army.</p>
            <p>And all you <hi>Congregational men,</hi> take heed of being deceived, all the World ſees you have been for every turn, and run to worſhip the riſing Sun, it ſheweth your weakneſſe and inſtabilities; one while the Lord is with this <hi>Parliament,</hi> then with the little <hi>Parliament,</hi> and then with the late <hi>Tyrant, Oliver,</hi> then with his <hi>Son Richard,</hi> then with this <hi>Parliament,</hi> and now with the <hi>Army;</hi> do you think that God followeth your wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, and is as uncertain as you are? no, he is a God of Truth and certainty, and loveth uprightneſs of heart, and doth hate all wicked doers and their wayes he wil <hi>curſe</hi> and <hi>blaſt</hi> them, as you ſee, he did the <hi>late Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> in all that he undertook; what and how hath this Nation been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done? how is the Armies and N vies behinde in pay and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth in debt 300 <hi>thouſand pounds,</hi> and yet theſe bleſſed Officers would
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119154:9"/>have the late <hi>Tyrants Wife</hi> have 8000 <hi>l. per annum,</hi> ſetled on her, and his eldeſt Son <hi>Richard</hi> 10000 <hi>l.</hi> and all his debts payed, which was 30000 <hi>l.</hi> do you not think theſe are like to prove eaſy maſters to you? do you think to eſcape them? no, for as the <hi>Duke of Medina Sidonya ſaid in</hi> 88. <hi>That his ſword knew no difference between a Catholick, and a Heretick, but he came to make way for his Maſter;</hi> So it will be with theſe men, they will not know you from others; therefore beware of your applications to them, and take the wiſe mans Counſel, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21.22. <hi>My ſon fear thou the Lord and the ſupream authority, and meddle not with them that are given to change, for their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both? For</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Nulla fides pietaſque viris qui caſtra ſequuntur.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Faithleſſe and Godleſſe, all things they can ſwollow,</l>
                     <l>Who wear cold Iron, and the wars do follow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <byline>Written by a Heathen, but made to true by thoſe that profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians.</byline>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
